Ted Hughes papers, 1940-1999
Emory University
Ted Hughes papers, 1940-1999
Hughes, Ted, 1930-1998.
Manuscript Collection No. 644
92.5 linear feet (186 boxes), 119 oversized papers (OP), and 1 oversized bound volume (OBV)
Papers of British poet laureate Ted Hughes including correspondence, writings by Hughes, materials relating to Sylvia Plath, writings by other authors, subject files, printed material, photographs, personal effects and memoriabilia, and audio-visual materials.
Emory University Manuscript, Archives, and Rare Book Library
Source
Purchase, 1997 with previous acquisitions and subsequent additions.
Restrictions on Access
Special restrictions apply. Access to selected files is restricted without the written permission of the copyright holder. Other selected files are closed for a period of twenty-five years (2022) or the lifetime of Carol Hughes, whichever is greater. See series scope notes for further details of specific materials covered by these restrictions.
Biographical Note
Ted Hughes was born on August 17th, 1930, the third child of Edith Farrar and William Hughes of Mytholmroyd, Yorkshire. When he was seven the family moved to Mexborough, a nearby mining town, where Hughes' parents ran a local newsagent's shop. There Hughes attended Mexborough Grammar School where he first began writing adventure stories and, later, verse, as he has explained, "when I discovered that what I wrote amused my classmates." Two poems from this period-among the earliest he wrote-survive in the Ted Hughes papers.
In 1948 Hughes won a scholarship to attend Pembroke College, Cambridge, but he first completed two years of national service as a ground wireless mechanic in an isolated RAF station in East Yorkshire. As he later recalled, there he had "nothing to do but read and reread Shakespeare and watch the grass grow." The landscape of his early years in Yorkshire left a permanent imprint on his later poetry as it also did on his life-long habits of sight.
In 1951 Hughes entered Pembroke College, Cambridge, where he first studied English literature, before switching in his third year to archaeology and anthropology. After completing his degree, Hughes divided his time between Cambridge and London where he drifted between a variety of odd jobs, among them that of a script reader for Pinewood Studios (?). In the years immediately after finishing at Cambridge, he also began publishing poems under a variety of pseudonyms in local literary magazines, among them Chequer, Granta, and Delta.
In February 1956 Hughes contributed four poems to a new literary magazine called St. Boltoph's Review. It was at a party to mark the launch of the new magazine that he first met the American poet Sylvia Plath who was in Cambridge on a Fulbright Scholarship. Soon after, on Bloomsday, June 16th, 1956, they were married in a small service at the church of St. George the Martyr in London.
At the time, Plath had already published numerous stories and poems in leading American magazines, and she soon introduced Hughes to an active program or regular manuscript submissions to leading literary magazines far beyond Cambridge. His first acceptance, as recorded in the scrapbook that Plath kept at the time, came with the publication of "Bawdry Embraced" in the August 1956 issue of Poetry magazine.
On the first anniversary of their meeting, Hughes learned that a collection of his poems, The Hawk in the Rain, had been selected by Marianne Moore, W.H. Auden, and Stephen Spender, as the best first collection out of 287 entries in a poetry competition organized by the Young Men's and Young Women's Hebrew Association of New York. With the publication of The Hawk in the Rain in both London and New York, Ted Hughes' literary career was launched.
From 1957 to 1959, Ted Hughes and Sylvia Plath lived in the United States where Plath taught at Smith College and Hughes at the University of Massachusetts. It was while living in the U.S. that Hughes met the artist Leonard Baskin who first suggested a sequence of poems based on a mythical crow figure and who later became a frequent collaborator on a number of fine press, artist's editions of Hughes' work. After a camping trip across the U.S. in the summer of 1959, Ted and Sylvia spent several weeks in residence at the Yaddo artists' colony in upstate New York. There Hughes worked on the poems that would later be collected in his second collection, Lupercal.
They returned to England in December and the following Spring Hughes learned that he had won both the Somerset Maugham Award and the Hawthorndon Prize (the latter for his second collection, Lupercal). A short time later their first child, Frieda, was born. Partly to support his new family, Hughes began a series of radio talks for the BBC's Listening and Writing program (later collected in Poetry in the Making), and in August the Hughes' moved into "Court Green," a former rectory in the village of North Tawton in Devon. In January 1962 their second child, Nicholas, was born.
During the fall of 1962 Hughes began seeing the artist Assia Wevill and soon after he and Sylvia Plath separated. While suffering from depression the following winter, Plath took her own life.
After Sylvia Plath's suicide, Hughes published a series of children's books, How the Whale Became (1963), The Earth-Owl and Other Moon People (1963), Nessie the Mannerless Monster (1964), and in 1965 he began serving as a judge for the National Children's Poetry Competition. He also, along with Daniel Weissbort, founded the journal Modern Poetry in Translation devoted to introducing the work of foreign language poets to English readers. Also in 1965, Hughes published Ariel, the posthumous collection of Sylvia Plath's poems upon which her reputation as a poet largely rests. In January 1967 Hughes and Assia Wevill's daughter Shura was born.
In 1967 Hughes published Wodwo, a collection of new poems, short stories, and a single radio play that he had previously recorded for the BBC. He also worked on a variety of other projects including serving as co-director of Poetry International, a major literary festival that included leading poets from around the world. He also collaborated with the director Peter Brook on a stage adaptation of Seneca's Oedipus for the National Theatre Company and translated a selection of poems by Yehuda Amichai (published in 1968).
In March 1969 Hughes' partner, Assia Wevill took her own life and that of Shura. Later that same year Hughes' mother also passed away.
In the late-1960s Hughes divided his time between Ireland and England and considered for a time moving permanently to Ireland; however, in 1969 he purchased Lumb Bank in his native Yorkshire. The following year he returned to Devon where he married Carol Orchard and where he settled permanently.
Beginning in 1970, and continuing over the next few years, Hughes published the cycle of crow poems that he had first begun at the suggestion of Leonard Baskin. In 1971 he also saw into print three collections of poems by Sylvia Plath, Crossing the Water, Lyonnesse, and Winter Trees. That same year he traveled to Iran where he again collaborated with Peter Brook, this time on a performance of Orghast which was first performed on the ruins of Persepolis.
In 1972 Ted and Carol Hughes purchased Moortown Farm in Devon which they managed with Carol's father, Jack Orchard. That same year, Faber and Faber issued a selection of Hughes' poems and an expanded edition of Crow. In 1974 Hughes received the prestigious Queen's Medal for Poetry. After the publication of his long poem Gaudete in 1977, Hughes published a series of collections that reflected his roots in the natural worlds of Yorkshire and Devon. These included Remains of Elmet (1979), Moortown Elegies (1979), and Moortown (1979), the latter dedicated to his father-in-law, Jack Orchard.
Hughes' interests in rural life and in children's education were combined in his work on behalf of the Farms for City Children program in the late 1970s. During this period and throughout the 1980s he continued to publish numerous works for children, and in 1982 he and Seamus Heaney collaborated on The Rattle Bag, an anthology of poems for children. In 1984 Ted Hughes was named Poet Laureate to the Queen, succeeding Sir John Betjeman. A collection of his laureate poems were collected in 1994 under the title Rain-Charm for the Duchy. Hughes' life-long interest--and love for--Shakespeare culminated in the 1992 study of his plays, Shakespeare and the Goddess of Complete Being.
After contributing to a collection of translations of Ovid in 1994, Hughes embarked on a series of translations of the Metamorphoses, which were published as Tales from Ovid in 1997. In February 1998 Hughes surprised the literary world with the publication of Birthday Letters, a series of 88 poems written to his first wife, Sylvia Plath. The critic Al Alvarez described them as "the most vulnerable he ever wrote, and also the saddest." Hughes' annus mirabilis continued with the completion of translations, in rapid succession, of three major dramatic works Racine's Phedre, Aeschylus' The Oresteia, and Euripides' Alcestis.
On October 28th, 1998 Ted Hughes died of cancer. In May 1999, the world paid tribute in a memorial service at London's Westminster Abbey.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of personal and literary papers of Ted Hughes from 1958-1992. The papers include correspondence, writings by Hughes including published and unpublished manucript and typescripts of poems and prose, materials relating to Sylvia Plath, writings by other authors that were sent to Hughes, subject files, printed material, photographs, personal effects and memoriabilia, and audio-visual materials. Major correspondents include Yehuda Amichai, Leonard Baskin, Martin Booth, Charles Causley, Janos Csokits, Seamus Heaney, Michael Horovitz, Lucas Myers, Peter Redgrove, Keith Sagar, Stephen Spender, Alan Sillitoe and Ruth Fainlight, and Daniel Weissbort. The collection also contains materials relating to Hughes that have been collected by the Library.
Arrangement Note
Organized into ten series: (1) Correspondence, (2) Writings by Ted Hughes, (3) Sylvia Plath, (4) Writings by others, (5) Subject files, (6) Printed material, (7) Photographs, (8) Personal effects and memorabilia, (9) Audio-visual materials, and (10) Collected materials.
Selected Search Terms
Personal Names
Amichai, Yehuda.; Baskin, Leonard, 1922-2000.; Booth, Martin.; Causley, Charles, 1917-; Csokits, János.; Fainlight, Ruth.; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-; Horovitz, Michael, 1935-; Merchant, W. Moelwyn (William Moelwyn), 1913-; Myers, Lucas.; Plath, Sylvia.; Redgrove, Peter.; Sagar, Keith M.; Spender, Stephen, 1909-1995.; Sillitoe, Alan.; Weissbort, Daniel.
Topical Terms
Children's literature, English; English drama--20th century.; English literature--20th century.; English poetry--20th century.; Poets, English--20th century.; Poets laureate--England.
Form/Genre Terms
Manuscripts.; Motion picture film.; Photographs.; Poems.; Radio scripts.; Sound recordings.
Occupation
Poet.
Separated Material
Emory University also holds the private library of Ted Hughes, as well as books formerly owned by Sylvia Plath. These materials may be located in the Emory University online catalog by searching for: Hughes, Ted, former owner and Plath, Sylvia, former owner.
Related Materials in This Repository
Ted Hughes, Letters to Janos Csokits, 1960-1998; Ted Hughes, Letters to Frieda Hughes, 1971-1997; Ted Hughes, Letters to Gerald Hughes, 1952-1991; Ted Hughes, Letters to W.S. and Dido Merwin, 1958-1969; Ted Hughes, Letters to Lucas Myers, 1955-1988; Ted Hughes, Letters to Peter Redgrove, ca. 1966-1984; Ted Hughes, Letters to Ben Sonnenberg, 1961-2000; Ted Hughes, Letters to Edna Wholey, ca. 1947-1951; Peter Fallon/Gallery Press collection; Seamus Heaney papers, Seamus Heaney collection, Anthony Hecht papers, Medbh McGuckian papers, Paul Muldoon papers; Edna O'Brien papers; Tom Paulin papers; Emma Tennant papers; Daniel Weissbort papers.
Description of Series
- Correspondence, 1959-1997, Series 1; Boxes 1-56
  Scope and Content Note
  The Ted Hughes papers contain extensive files of correspondence dating from 1959-1997. The largest part of this correspondence is located in Series 1, though letters related to specific projects or activities may also be found in the subject files located in Series 5. Over the years, Hughes maintained different systems of filing for these letters. For many years he maintained an alphabetical correspondence file which contained letters from friends and colleagues with whom he had sustained correspondence. This alphabetical arrangement has been preserved in Subseries 1.1. Subseries 1.2, Business correspondence, includes correspondence with his publishers Faber and Faber, Harper and Row, as well as correspondence related to his work on behalf of the Arvon Foundation. Subseries 1.3 contains general correpondence that was not alphabetized by Hughes. Letters from individuals for whom there was an existing alphabetical file in Subseries 1.1 have been moved to that subseries. Hughes also received a large amount of correspondence from children responding to his children's books. These letters may be found in Subseries 1.4. Holograph or typescript drafts of letters written by Ted Hughes or photocopies of outgoing letters by him are located in Subseries 1.5. Correspondence both to and from Ted Hughes acquired from other sources can be found in Series 10. Any correspondence that was found on the verso of works was photocopied and added to this series, with a note on the bottom of the photocopy as to where the original correspondence is located in the collection.
  Arrangement Note
  Organized into five subseries: (1.1) Alphabetical correspondence files, (1.2) Business correspondence, (1.3) General correspondence, (1.4) Children's correspondence, and (1.5) Ted Hughes' correspondence.
  Restrictions on Access
  Special restrictions apply: Subseries 1.1, Alphabetical correspondence files, letters written by Janos Csokits and Daniel Weissbort are restricted and require the permission of the copyright holder in writing in order to be examined. Letters from Seamus Heaney are closed to researchers. In addition, other selected letters are also restricted without the permission of the copyright holder.
  - Alphabetical correspondence files, 1959-1996, Subseries 1.1; Boxes 1-10
    The subseries consists of incoming correspondence arranged in alphabetical order from 1959-1996. Much of this correspondence is of both a personal and a professional nature. Hughes maintained a lively literary correspondence with a number of prominent writers, translators, and poets including Yehuda Amichai, Leonard Baskin, Janos Csokits, Seamus Heaney, Michael Horovitz, W. Moelwyn Merchant, Peter Redgrove, Keith Sagar, Stephen Spender, Alan Sillitoe and Ruth Fainlight, and Daniel Weissbort. There are also letters from family members including Sylvia Plath's mother, Aurelia Plath, as well as a few letters from his sister, Olywn and his brother Gerald.
    Arranged in alphabetical order, with restricted correspondence filed at the end of the subseries.
    - Abse, Dannie, June 1967-December 1987, 10 items (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Alvarez, Al, November 1977-December 1984, 10 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Amichai, Yehuda, June 1970-November 1977, 32 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Amichai, Yehuda, January 1978-June 1986, 31 items (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Amichai, Yehuda, December 1986-November 1994 and undated, 22 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Armitage, Simon, August 1992-September 1993, 2 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Baker, Kenneth, May 1987-June 1994 and undated, 14 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Baldwin, Michael, May 1981-February 1994, 23 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Baldwin, Michael, undated, 24 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Baldwin, Michael [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Baskin, Leonard, May 1959-December 1969, 5 items (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Baskin, Leonard, January 1970-June 1978, 23 items (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Baskin, Leonard and Tobias, April 1980-September 1983, 23 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Baskin, Leonard, January 1984-September 1986, 36 items (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Baskin, Leonard, April 1987-August 1989, 17 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Baskin, Leonard, February 1990-May 1993, 14 items (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Baskin, Leonard, undated, 8 items (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Betjeman, John, June 1976-April 1983, 11 items (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Booth, Martin, October 1971-August 1979, 37 items (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Booth, Martin, June 1980-May 1985, 20 items (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Booth, Martin, February 1986-April 1993, 31 items (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Bragg, Melvin, January 1983-September 1989 and undated, 10 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Brandt, Bill, August 1978-September 1978, 3 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Brook, Peter, July 1975-October 1994, 15 items (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Brophy, Brigid, July 1979, 2 items (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Brown, George Mackay, October 1982, 1 item (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Brownjohn, Alan and Sandra, May 1977-May 1994 and undated, 26 items (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Bunting, Basil, December 1981-March 1983, 2 items (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Causley, Charles, July 1972-October 1987, 28 items (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Causley, Charles, June 1988-September 1998, 29 items (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Clarke, Gillian, March 1978-April 1994 and undated, 21 items (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Cooke, Barrie, August 1974-January 1994 and undated, 30 items (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Cooke, Barrie, undated, 36 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Cooke, Barrie, undated, 31 items (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Cox, Brian, February 1978-December 1993, 14 items (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Duncan, Ronald, November 1971-October 1973, 3 items (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Dunn, Douglas, November 1972-January 1991 and undated, 13 items (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Dyson, A.E. (Tony), August 1977-May 1992, 30 items (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Eliot, T.S. [See Subseries 8.1: Blue scrapbook, 1956-1963] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Enright, D.J. (Dennis), July 1976-May 1983, 16 items (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Ewart, Gavin, January 1977-February 1981, 7 items (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Faas, Ekbert, October 1970-November 1992, 9 items (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Fainlight, Harry, undated, 5 items (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Fainlight, Ruth [See Alan Sillitoe] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Fallon, Peter, January 1980-September 1993 and undated, 9 items [See also Series 5: Gallery Press, Peter Fallon] (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Feuer, Donya, July 1974-June 1993, 14 items (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Feuer, Donya, undated, 6 items (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Gammage, Nick, May 1980-September 1995, 39 items (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Gifford, Terry and Neil Roberts, March 1979, 1 item (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Gillespie, I.S., February 1993-March 1994 and undated, 16 items (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Godwin, Fay, July 1973-June 1979, 37 items (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Godwin, Fay, December 1980-January 1995, 55 items (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Godwin, Fay, undated, 15 items (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Godwin, Fay [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Gunn, Thom, May 1968-August 1992, 28 items (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Gunn, Thom [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Guppy, Shusha, January 1971-December 1984, 27 items (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Guppy, Shusha, January 1985-September 1994, 17 items (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Hall, Donald, March 1994, 1 item (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Hamburger, Michael, March 1975-September 1994 and undated, 31 items (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Hart, Henry [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Hart, Josephine, June 1992 and undated, 7 items (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Heaney, Seamus [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Herbert, Zbigniew, July 1983, 1 item (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Heseltine, Michael and Anne, January 1985-March 1994 and undated, 27 items (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Hofmann, Michael, March 1992-August 1994, 9 items (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Horovitz, Michael, August 1971-October 1983, 18 items (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Horovitz, Michael, November 1983-September 1996, 22 items (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Horovitz, Michael, Announcements, 13 items (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Horovitz, Michael, Articles and Poems, 19 items (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Hughes, Frieda, n.d., 2 items (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Hughes, Gerald, April 1965, 1 item (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Hughes, Glyn, August 1974-March 1994 and undated, 17 items (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Hughes, Glyn [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Hughes, Nicholas, n.d., 1 item (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Hughes, Olwyn, May 1964-July 1994, 38 items (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Hughes, Olwyn, undated, 13 items (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Huws, Daniel, February 1977-October 1994 and undated, 23 items (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Jong, Erica, April 1971-March 1973, 5 items (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Keen, Peter, November 1973-March 1989 and undated, 25 items (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Larkin, Philip, June 1975-August 1985 and undated, 13 items (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Logue, Christopher, August 1976-March 1986, 6 items (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Lowell, Robert, October 1966-December 1967, 2 items (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - MacBeth, George and Lisa St. Aubin de Teran, May 1973-October 1993 and undated, 21 items (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - MacLean, Sorley, June 1991, 2 items (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - McCaughey, Terence, August 1979-May 1991 and undated, 9 items (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Martin, E. W. (Ernest), September 1978-May 1993 and undated, 19 items (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Maugham, W. Somerset, May 1960, 1 item (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Merchant, W. Moelwyn, November 1971-November 1989, 31 items (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Merchant, W. Moelwyn, February 1990-March 1993, 40 items (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Merwin, Bill and Dido, December 1970-July 1988, 4 items (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Miller, Karl, September 1979-January 1988, 10 items (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Minami, Akira, December 1981-May 1993 and undated, 11 items (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Mindlin, Murray, September 1970-October 1979 and undated, 10 items (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Mindlin, Murray [See Restricted correspondence] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Mitchell, Adrian, November 1978-March 1996 and undated, 21 items (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Mitchison, Naomi, undated, 1 item (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Montague, John, 1961-1980, 3 items (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Monteith, Charles [See Subseries 8.1: Blue scrapbook, 1956-1963] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Morpurgo, Michael, September 1977-June 1990, 10 items (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Muldoon, Paul, October 1983-January 1985, 2 items (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Murphy, Richard, September 1971-December 1987 and undated, 17 items (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Myers, Lucas, ca.1956-May 1994, 21 items (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Myers, Lucas, undated, 27 items (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Myers, Lucas, undated, 15 items (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Nicholson, Emma, July 1988-February 1992 and undated, 11 items (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Norris, Leslie, January 1975-May 1993, 11 items (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - O'Brien, Edna, 1981 and undated, 5 items (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Osborne, Charles, May 1981-December 1988 and undated, 21 items (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Paulin, Tom, May 1992-May 1994, 4 items (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Pennatti, Camillo, February 1972-March 1993 and undated, 35 items (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Pilinszky, Janos, February 1972-November 1978 and undated, 12 items (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Plath, Aurelia, November 1972-November 1982, 19 items (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Plath, Aurelia, April 1983-August 1991 and undated, 21 items (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Plath, Warren [See Aurelia Plath] (Box -, Folder -)
    - Raine, Craig, March 1979-November 1984, 40 items (Box 5, Folder 20)